Let's get some updates on the tiny human
brains that you can grow from stem
cells. Yes, there's an entire field
where people just grow tiny human brains
and have them do stuff like run
computation. They can embody them in
game world. They have both long-term and
short-term memory and they are
technically sentient because they're
capable of having an experience. This
research group decided to embody them in
Pac-Man and used electric shocks to
teach them. I've seen multiple papers
where people try to teach them with
various input. They do generally seem to
do better when they're given both
positive and negative reinforcement.
This one bugged me because they
essentially shocked them until they did
something right. One of the major
limitations on brain organoids is that
they tend to suffer from hypoxia because
they do not have, you know, a heart or
largely a bloodb brain barrier, but
there's been a great deal of progress in
that. This group gave them veins. So,
they essentially grew vascular
organoids, so a vascular system that's
grown from stem cells along with the
brain organoids and 3D printed veins
directly into their core. So this way
they can get oxygen and they do a lot
better. From what I've read, they can be
kept alive for a year or more and they
tend to follow the development of a
preterm baby. Yes, they have found delta
and beta brain wave. So delta are the
ones that are associated with things
like being in a coma or generally
asleep. Stuff like beta and alpha is
associated with wakefulness. And while
they're not as complex as you know a
human brain, they are growing more
complex the longer they're kept alive.
You can in fact combine a organoid with
AI. Although there are a lot of
limitations. You can't run an entire LLM
on a brain organoid any more than you
could run an entire LLM on your brain.
But there are things that you are good
at. Language recognition, for example,
is one of the things that they excel at.
And people have used brain organoids
with AI and let them learn unsupervised.
And they learn to recognize the voices
of the researchers. This group taught
them braille. Now, when assemblids are
built, that means multiple brain
organoids and other organs put together,
they're essentially making a tiny body,
people have been learning how to do
this, essentially blind, and they keep
looking to nature to try to manufacture
a better form for them to use. It did
surprise me that the more complex brain
organoids are actually better at doing
computation. I would have expected
single cell types would be efficient,
but no, multiple cell types, multiple
loes, they do better. And that's one of
the reasons that people have been
combining brain organoids into loed
brains for robotics. In this case, you
know, that was a brain organoid system
that played Pac-Man. I I still haven't
quite gotten over that one. They just
gave them electric shocks until they
found food so that they could get a
break from the stress. This is why
they're considered technically sentient
because they have the capacity to feel
something and they have the capacity to
want something. Going after food in
Pac-Man and avoiding the ghost because
you'll get an electric shock does seem
remarkably sentient. Now, they're not
technically conscious. Consciousness is
a very difficult thing to demonstrate
because it's more philosophical than
scientific. How do we demonstrate that
something has the concept of self? If
you can just connect them by axons and
they work together, do they have a
concept of self? I do not know. We won't
know until they tell us. And at the rate
that this field is moving, they might
tell us one day soon. Since this field
is moving quite so fast, I would like to
bring us back to the question of what is
ethical? At what point are we
experimenting on tissue versus
experimenting on a being? Because at
what point does something become a
being? Am I a being? I don't have
answers to